<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A letter vvritten by Gregory the XV. Pope of Rome, to the French King To our most dearely beloued son health in Iesus Christ, Louis the 13. the most Christian King of France. According to the French coppie printed at Paris. 1621.</title>
            <title>Lettre envoyée au Roy. English and French</title>
            <author>Gregory XV, Pope, 1554-1623.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A02219</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 12356</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103429</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839183</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839183</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3584</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A02219)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3584)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 578:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A letter vvritten by Gregory the XV. Pope of Rome, to the French King To our most dearely beloued son health in Iesus Christ, Louis the 13. the most Christian King of France. According to the French coppie printed at Paris. 1621.</title>
                  <title>Lettre envoyée au Roy. English and French</title>
                  <author>Gregory XV, Pope, 1554-1623.</author>
                  <author>Louis XIII, King of France, 1601-1643.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8, 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by Bernard Alsop] for N[athaniel] B[utter],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's and publisher's names from STC.</note>
                  <note>"Lettre enuoyee au Roy", the French text, has separate pagination and title page with imprint "A Paris. 1621."; register is continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>France --  History --  Louis XIII, 1601-1643.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-10</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>A LETTER WRITTEN <hi>BY</hi> GREGORY THE XV.</p>
                  <p>Pope of Rome, to the French King.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>To our moſt dearely beloued ſon health in Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> Louis <hi>the 13. the moſt Chriſtian King of France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>According to the French coppie printed at <hi>Paris.</hi> 1621.</p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>London Printed for <hi>N. B.</hi> 1621.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:2"/>
                  <head>A LETTER WRITTEN BY <hi>GRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the 15. Pope of Rome <hi>to the French King.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O our moſt dearely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued ſonne, health in Ieſus Chriſt, and our Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call benediction,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme greatnes of the actions of your Royall valour, which haue drawne vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſpirits of all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, yeeld no ſmall contentment vnto our Paternall care, together with the glory of your armies, &amp; the hope of your triumphs: for when we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider, with much griefe, the impietie of the heretickes, hiding themſelues in certaine places without all doubt or feare, and in other places, vſurping the body of a cruel gouernme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, we are now moued to giue thanks vnto the God of armies, who in ſo fit a time for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3584:3"/>
warre, inciteth your Maieſtie to enter into armes for the defence of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke religion. O moſt notable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prentiſage of a royall Iuſtice, &amp; wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of a moſt Chriſtian king, for is it not admirable, that in that age where in others are wont to paſſe their time in pleaſure and delights, moued ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by delicatenes, faintnes of heart, you imploy the ſame, not onely gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly but alſo happily. To appeaſe differences, to march forward in arms &amp; to beſiege the hereticks holds and ſtrong places, &amp; that not without the counſell of God, in whoſe kingdome kings liue: what? is it credible that in the beginning of your yong yeeres, you ſhould be endowed with ſo hau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie a heart as to vndertake ſo great &amp; difficult a matter, &amp; that the dangers &amp; difficulties that haue bin the cauſe to daunt other mens hearts, ſhould moue &amp; incite you to ſo great a cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage? Inioy (deare ſonne) that renown which your famous name hath ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned, and follow that God which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3584:3"/>
fighteth with you, to the end, that as at this preſent euery man eſteemeth you to be the thunder bolt of warre, and the buckler of peace, you may be held and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed by all men, in time to come, the prayſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and the glory of all the world. From the moſt high top of our Apoſtolical dignity, wherunto the hand of God hath brought vs, (although vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of ſo great a charge) with our whole ſpirit and affection we aſſiſt your armes, and by our frequent and dayly prayers prepare diuine remedies for you. And although wee doubt not but that you wil ſtil with conſtancy perſiſt there in euen vnto the end, being incited ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto by vs, and as by your vertue you haue vndertaken the ſame, we hope you will not take it in euill part to bee more and more encouraged therein by good exhortation, that it may apparantly bee ſeene that wee haue a great care of you and of the aduancement of the true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and that wee will giue place to your glory, you are hitherto much bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vnto God, for his great liberalties, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3584:4"/>
as we hope and wiſh both together; you ſhal be much more bound vnto him for the ſame in time to come, and it is to be beleeued that your ſpirit ſo highly eleua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and endowed with celeſtiall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and not with the precepts of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane wiſedome, as you haue alwayes well vnderſtood, that the foundations of kingdomes are grounded and ſet vpon the truth of one Orthodoxall faith, and that as long as God is not the keeper and preſeruer of townes, neuer any principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie can aſſuredly ſubſiſt. Iudg with how much fidelitie they will defend your royall throane that haue caſt the Saints out of their temple., and that haue at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted the meanes to extirpe them out of the number of the bleſſed, yea and out of Paradiſe, who with an impious teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rete condemne the inſtitutions of our anceſtors, the cuſtomes of kings, the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of Popes, and the ceremonies of the Church: theſe are the troubles of our an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient common wealth, and the reproch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of France, that God, Emperor of kings hath reſerued you to extinguiſh them in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:3584:4"/>
your yong yeares. Know that all Europe that hangeth in ſuſpence of the euent of your warre, hope ſhortly vnder your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction to ſet vp their ſails vpon the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean, to the end that that place which ſerues for the Seat &amp; defence of rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous heretiks, may ſerue for a marke vnto the poſteritie of your great victories. We are certainely perſwaded, that neither feare, nor inconſtancy can nor wil diuert you from your enterpriſe: neuertheles, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes remember, that the Saints whoſe honour men defend, ayde and aſſiſt that Prince, that vndertaketh the protection of religion, and with him fight as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panions in the warre: you ſhall not, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt fayle of God to be fauourable vnto you in the waters, where at other times, hee made the land firme as it had bin drie ground, and where the waters diuided on both ſides ſerued as a wall giuing paſſage vnto his army: From whence wee may aſſuredly hope, that after you ſhall haue eſtabliſhed an aſſured peace in your Realme, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come and vanquiſhed the impietie that
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:3584:5"/>
raighneth therein, you may one day by your great victories, ioyne the Eaſt and the Weſt together, imitating the glory of your anceſtors, that yeelded as great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour vnto the Popes exhortations as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the commandements of God. Holy S. <hi>Louis</hi> inuiteth you thereunto, whoſe name, as well as his actions, you beare &amp; imitate. The principall of your race in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite you thereunto, who in defending the Apoſtolical authority, and enlarging religion, laid the good and aſſured foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dations of your royal houſe, follow (moſt deare ſonne) the emament of the whole world, the commandements of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, conuert your choller and indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion towards thoſe people that haue not knowne God, to the end that in heauen you may obtaine the treaſures of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine mercy, whereunto, by our Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall authority, with extraordinary affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction we giue our bleſſing.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Giuen in Rome in S. Maria maior, vnder the Fiſhermans ring. <date>1621. the firſt yeare of our Pontificat.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="fre">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:5"/>
                  <p>LETTRE ENVOYEE AV ROY, PAR NOSTRE SAINCT Pere le Pape GREGOIRE XV. <hi>ſur les affaires de ce temps.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <figure/>
                  <p>A PARIS. 1621.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="letter">
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:6"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:6"/>
                  <head>A NOSTRE TRES CHER fils en Ieſus-Chriſt LOVYS XIII. Roy des Francois tres-Chriſtien.</head>
                  <byline>GREGOIRE PAPE XV.</byline>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>OSTRE tres cher fils en Ieſus-Chriſt ſalut &amp; noſtre benediction Apoſtolique. </salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Les hauts faicts de vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtre valeur Royale, qui ont attiré ſur euxles eſprits des Chreſtiens, aportent bien du contentement à noſtre ſoing paternel parmy la gloire de vos armes,</hi> &amp; <hi>l'eſperance de vos triomphes: car comme nous conſiderons auec beau coup de regrers l'im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieté des heretiques croupiſſants en certaines lieux ſans peur &amp; ſans crainte: en d'autres exercans le corps d'vne cruelle domination, nous remercions maintenant le Dieu des armees d'auoir en vn temps ſi opportun pour la guerre, fait prendre les armes a</hi> V. M. <hi>pour la defenſe de la Religion Catholique. Obel apprentiſſage d'vne Royale Milice, &amp; digne d vn Roy Tres-Chreſtien? Quelle merueille, que l'aage que les autres ont accouſtumé de paſſer en jeux &amp; delicer par vne certaine molleſſe</hi> &amp; <hi>faineantiſe, vous l'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployez auſsi genereuſement qu'heureuſement à appai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer les differents, à conduire les armees,</hi> &amp; <hi>aſsieger les places des heretiques?</hi> &amp; <hi>le tout non ſans le conſeil
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:3584:7"/>
de Dieu, au Royaume duquelvinent les Roys. Quoy? eſt il croyable qu'aux premiers abbords de voſtre ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſcence vous ayez entrepris vn oeuure ſi releué &amp; ſi difficile, &amp; que les dangers &amp; difficultez qui ont arreſté le cours des autres, ayent incité la grandeur de voſtre courage? Iouyſſez (tres-cher fils) de la reno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mee que voſtre nom a acquis, &amp; ſuyuez le Dieu qui combat auec vous afin que comme maintenaut vn cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cun vous, tient pour le fouldre de la guerre,</hi> &amp; <hi>le bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clier de la paix, vous ſoyez eſtimé de tous à l'aduenir la louange d'Iſrael, &amp; la gloire de tout le monde.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Du plus haut ſommet de noſtre dignité Apoſtolique, où la main dubou Dieu nous a conduict, bien que in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digne de ceſte charge, nous aſsiſtons d'eſprit &amp; d'affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vos armes,</hi> &amp; <hi>par nos frequantes prieres, vous preparo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s les diuins ramedes Et bien que nous ne douti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons point que vous n'y mettiez la derniere main auec heaucoup de conſtance, à ce inuité par nous, &amp; comme par voſtre vertu vous auez entrepris, toutes-fois ne trouuez point mannais d'y eſtre emflammé dauantage par exhortations, afin qu'il parroiſſe que nous ſommes ſoigneux du bien &amp; de l'aduancement de la vraye Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> &amp; <hi>que nous voulons donner lieu à voſtre gloi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re. Vous eſtes iuſqu'à ceſte heure grandement rede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uable à Dieu de ſes liberalitez, &amp; comme nous eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons &amp; ſouhaittons tout enſemble, vous le ſerez bien dauantage à l'aduenir:</hi> &amp; <hi>il eſt croyable que voſtre eſprit ſi reuelé</hi> &amp; <hi>imbu a'vne celeſte doctrine,</hi> &amp; <hi>non point des preceptes de quelque ſapience humaine, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me vous auez touſiours bien entendu que les fonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens des Royanmes ſont appuiez ſur la verité d'vne Foy Orthodoxe,</hi> &amp; <hi>de fait tant que Dieu ne ſera point gardien des villes, tamais aucune principaute ne
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:3584:7"/>
ſubſiſtera auec aſſurance. Que l'on iuge auec combien de fidelitè defendront voſtre ſiege Royal, ceux qui ont iettè les Saincts meſme de leurs temples, &amp; qui ont ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te les moyens meſme de les oſter du nombre des bien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heureux, voire du Paradis, ceux qui auec vne impie temerité condamnent les Inſtitutions de nos majeurs, les couſtemes des Roys, les Decrets des Papes,</hi> &amp; <hi>les ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies de l'Egliſe; ce ſont les troubles de noſtre Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publique ancienne,</hi> &amp; <hi>les reproches de la France, que Dieu Empereur des Roys vous à reſeruè pour eſtre e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaints durant le cours de vos ieunes ans. Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chez maintenant que toute l'Europe qui eſt en ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens de l'euenement de vos armes, attandde bien toſt ſoubs voſtre conduitte dreſſer ſes voiles ſur l'Ocean, afin que lieu qui ſert d'aſile</hi> &amp; <hi>de defence aux heretiques rebelles, ſerue à la poſterité pour mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que de vos victoires. Nous ſcauons bien que ny la crainte, ny l'inconſtance ne vous deſtourneront iamais de voſtre entrepriſe: ſouuenès vous toutesfois que les Saints deſquels on defend l'honneur, aſsiſtent au Prince qui prend la protection de la religion,</hi> &amp; <hi>combattent auec luy comme des compagnons de guerre. Vous ne manqurez ſans doubte d'auoir Dieu fauorable ſur les meſmes caues dont autres foisil endurcit les flors ſoubs les pieds comme de la terre,</hi> &amp; <hi>dont les ondes diuiſees decà</hi> &amp; <hi>delà ſeruants comme de murailes donnoient paſſage à ſon armee: pour lors nous pourrons eſperer aſſeureme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t qu'a pres auoir mis en voſtre Roiame vn bo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſtabliſſeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> &amp; <hi>do<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pté l'impietè quiſ'y renco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tre, vous pourrez quelque iour par vos victoires ioindre l'Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent à l'Occident imitant la gloire de vos anceſtres, qui ont porté autant d'honneur aux exhortations des Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes qu'aux commandements de Dieu. A cela vous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uite le tres-ſainct Louys le nom duquel vous portez
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:3584:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>
auſibien comme vous imitez les actions. Les premiers de voſtre race vous y connenient, leſquels en defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant lauctorité Apoſtolique, eſtendant la religion, ont ietté de bons</hi> &amp; <hi>aſſeurez fondemens de voſtre Royalle maiſons Suyueztres-cher fils, l'ornement du monde, les commandements du pere Verſez voſtre colere</hi> &amp; <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation ſur les peuples qui n'ont point cogneu Dieu afin que dans le Ciel vous acqueriez les threſors de la diuine miſericorde à</hi> V. M. <hi>à laquelle par noſtre au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritè Apoſtolique vous donons auec affection extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinaire noſtre benediction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <dateline>Donné à Rome à ſaincte Marie Maieur ſoubs l'an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neau du Peſcheur, <date>1621. l'An premier de noſtre Pontificat.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3584:8"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
